A Guide to the Virginia Tech Ring and Class Collections, 1910-2015
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Virginia Tech Ring and Class Collections, 1910-2015
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 31/13/3
5.83 Cubic Feet; 11 boxes
The Virginia Tech Ring and Class Collections document the work of the Ring Design Committee, Ring Dance Committee, and individual classes at VPI, including their reunions. Items include ring design proposals and collection brochures, invitations and flyers for ring dances, and memorabilia for graduating classes and class reunions.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Virginia Tech Ring and Class Collections was transferred to Special Collections.
Biographical/Historical Note
Each year, the junior class officers and student appointees form the Ring Design Committee, which works with the Virginia Tech Alumni Association and a jewelry vendor to design a class ring collection. The collection, unique to each class, is named in honor of a Virginia Tech alum, emeritus, president, or other administrator. The tradition originates to 1911, when the classes of 1911, 1912, 1913, and 1914 designed the first class rings. Symbols from these early years have become traditional elements: eagles, campus buildings, and a chain symbolizing unity around the stone.
In the spring of their junior year, the Ring Dance Committee holds a dance to represent the transition from junior to senior. At the Ring Dance, students wear their dates' rings on ribbons of the class colors. When the Corps of Cadets form the shape of the class year and perform the sabre arch, the students exchange their rings to the tune of "Moonlight and VPI," written by Fred Waring and Charles Gaynor for Virginia Tech in 1939. The Virginia Tech Swine Club releases a small pig onto the dance floor, which started as a prank by members of the Corps of Cadets over 30 years ago. Then the attendees move to the Drillfield to watch fireworks, listen to "Sliver Taps," and witness the firing of the school cannon "Skipper."
Scope and Content
The Virginia Tech Ring and Class Collections document the work of the Ring Design Committee, Ring Dance Committee, and individual classes at VPI. Items include ring design proposals from potential vendors; brochures about the committees, design processes, and class ring collections; invitations, flyers, and tickets for the Ring Dance; and such artifacts as wax molds of the rings, banners from events, and t-shirts, glassware, and other memorabilia given to students. There are also printed materials and memorabilia from class reunions and a poster about the history of the Virginia Tech Class Ring Tradition.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by class year.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Record Group Vertical Files
Two framed Class of 1944 Ring and Ring Dance posters are part of the Art Collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Class of 1910
  - Reunion materials, 1950 (Box 1)
- Class of 1925
  - Class Ring, inscribed D.L.W., 1925 (Box 4)
- Class of 1927
  - Alumni recollection, ca. 2001 (Box 1)
- Class of 1930
  - 50th Anniversary Drink Glass, 1980 (Box 4)
- Class of 1934
  - Graduation and reunion materials, 1934, 1984, 1988, 1994 (Box 1)
  - 60th Anniversary Drink Glass, 1994 (Box 8)
- Class of 1935
  - Reunion materials, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Ring Dance invitation and booklet, 1934 (Box 1)
- Class of 1937
  - Ring dance invitation, 1936 (Box 1)
- Class of 1939
  - Class ring and ring dance materials, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
- Class of 1944
  - Reunion materials, 1989 (Box 1)
- Class of 1956
  - Class Ring, 1956 (Box 4)
- Class of 1964
  - Ring design materials (Box 1)
- Class of 1965
  - Ring design materials (Box 1)
  - Poster (Box 5)
- Class of 1967
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
  - Ring collection booklet (Box 11)
  - Poster (Box 5)
- Class of 1969
  - Ring collection booklet (Box 11)
- Class of 1972
  - Tech Showmen drink glass (Box 8)
- Class of 1976
  - Ring collection booklet (Box 11)
- Class of 1977
  - Ring collection booklet (Box 11)
- Class of 1980
  - Ring collection booklet (Box 11)
- Class of 1984
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
- Class of 1985
  - Ring collection brochure (Box 1)
- Class of 1988
  - Ring collection brochure (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Box 5)
- Class of 1989
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
- Class of 1990
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
- Class of 1991
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
  - Poster (Box 5)
- Class of 1992
  - Class officer and Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
- Class of 1993
  - Class officer and Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
  - Jostens ring proposal (Box 10)
- Class of 1994
  - Ring design materials (Box 1)
  - Ring designs (Box 5)
  - Balfour ring proposal (Box 10)
  - Artcarved ring proposal (Box 10)
- Class of 1995
  - Balfour ring proposal (Box 10)
  - Jostens ring proposal (Box 10)
- Class of 1996
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
  - Wax rings (Box 4)
- Class of 1997
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook (Box 7)
  - Jostens ring proposal (Box 10)
- Class of 1998
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 1)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 1999
  - Ring Committee and dance materials (Box 1)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
  - Table card (Box 5)
- Class of 2000
  - Ring Proposal (Box 2)
  - Planning (Box 2)
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 2)
- Class of 2001
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 2)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2002
  - Ring premiere and dance materials (Box 2)
  - Gobos (Light stencils) (Box 4)
  - Glass candle (Box 4)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
  - Posters (Box 9)
- Class of 2003
  - Ring premiere and dance materials (Box 5)
  - Frame (Box 4)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2004
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 2)
  - Ring design poster (Box 5)
  - Wax rings (Box 4)
  - Pen (Box 4)
  - Mug (Box 4)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2005
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 2)
  - Frame (Box 4)
  - Wax rings (Box 4)
  - Mug (Box 4)
  - Posters (Box 5)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
  - Corps of Cadets Mug (Box 8)
- Class of 2006
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 2)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - Key ring (Box 4)
  - Plastic cup (Box 4)
  - Ping pong ball (Box 4)
  - Posters (Box 5)
  - Handkerchief (Box 6)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2007
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - T-shirts (Box 6)
- Class of 2008
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - T-shirts (Box 6)
- Class of 2009
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - Poster (Box 5)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2010
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Poster (Box 5)
  - T-shirts (Box 6)
  - Handkerchief (Box 6)
  - Ring Dance drink glass (Box 8)
- Class of 2011
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2012
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - Poster (Box 5)
  - T-shirt (Box 6)
- Class of 2013
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Drink glass (Box 4)
  - Eyeglass holder (Box 4)
  - Poster (Box 5)
  - Ring Premiere and Dance koozie (Box 8)
  - Two Ring Dance pins (Box 8)
  - Two Ring Ribbons (Box 8)
  - T-shirts (Box 9)
- Class of 2014
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Ring Premiere Eyeglass holder (Box 4)
  - Wine glass (Box 4)
  - Poster (Box 5)
  - Ring Premiere and Dance koozie (Box 8)
  - Two Ring Ribbons (Box 8)
  - T-shirts (Box 9)
  - Ring Dance banner (Box 9)
- Class of 2015
  - Ring design and dance materials (Box 3)
  - Ring Premiere Tumbler (Box 4)
  - Key ring (Box 4)
  - Poster (Box 5)
  - Ring Premiere and Dance koozie (Box 8)
  - Ring Premiere and Dance flying disk (Box 8)
  - Two Ring Ribbons (Box 8)
  - T-shirt (Box 9)
  - Kickoff concert banner (Box 9)
- Assorted poster
  - Virginia Tech Class Ring Tradition Poster, undated (Box 5)